Updated: Aug/24/2022

CURRICULUM VITAE

Somang Nam

Toronto, ON Canada Phone: +1-416-897-5008

Email: somang.nam@gmail.com

I am an individual with a passion for many technical fields, from implementing efficient algorithmic solutions to delivering accessible solutions. I like to tackle challenges by using data to discuss with others. I sit at the junction between Software Engineering, Machine Learning application, and Human-Computer Interaction (UI/UX).

As a software engineer, my technical expertise spans many areas of Computer Science, including algorithm and system design, full-stack web development, data engineering, data analytics, machine learning applications, and game development.

As a scientific researcher, I can design and conduct interdisciplinary research in the field of Human-Computer Interaction, Accessibility, and Human Factors (digital ergonomics). I can perform mixed data analytics (both quantitative and qualitative) and share the findings with academic or public audiences using visualizations and presentations.

Google Scholar Github LinkedIn Research Gate

Degrees

Ph.D.	Industrial Engineering - Human Factors	University of Toronto	2021
M.Sc.	Computer Science - HCI	Toronto Metropolitan University	2016
H.B.Sc.	Computer Science, Mathematics & Ethnomusicology	University of Toronto	2013

Certificates

- Data Engineering, Big Data, and Machine Learning on GCP by Google Cloud on Coursera (<u>credential</u>)
- Foundations of User Experience (UX) Design by Google on Coursera (credential)
- Deep Learning Institute Certificate of Competency: Fundamentals of Deep Learning for Computer Vision by NVIDIA (<u>credential</u>)
- Member of IEEE Computer Society Technical Committee on Semantic Computing No.96579108

Employment history

I've spent some time as an adjunct lecturer/professor or as a teaching assistant at the university, which is listed <u>separately</u>.

Year (s)	Organization Name, Position Title and specific responsibilities
2022 - current	The Bank of Nova Scotia, - Senior Data Engineer - Tech Lead (2022, July - Current) - Data Enablement, Customer Insights, Data & Analytics
	 Data Engineer Manager (2022, May - July) Developed data profiling module using PySpark, Python Designed anomaly detection module using BigQuery Machine Learning tool
2021 - 2022	National Research Council Canada, Technical Officer-3, development of an open-access platform that calculates quantities related to light and lighting stimuli based on scientific documents (< 25k monthly traffic). React, Node, MathJS, ChartJS
2018	PAVO Digital - Toronto Metropolitan University, Software Developer, caption editing software development using ElectronJS and Python
2016	Toronto Metropolitan University, Research Assistant - Data Engineer for a web crawling project about social commerce platform data using Python and Selenium
2013	Universal Music Group (NBC Universal Toronto), Mobile Developer, implemented an Android application prototype for music remix using Youtube API
2012	University of Toronto, Research Assistant - Data Engineer, iSchool and political economics collaborative <u>project</u> . Developed text data mining pipelines using Python from the Twitter accounts of U.S. congress candidates (~750 accounts). Also collected politically active Twitter users (2.2 million) and a total of 500,000 tweets over six weeks.

Projects (personal and team collaboration)

Projects other than school coursework and exclusion of professional experiences. Thesis and research projects are included.

Year	Project	
2022	- Scraping off some of the commercial websites for wristwatches, using Selenium and SQLite3	
- Worked on a generative art project with multiple artists, using the proces and GlitchJS		
	 - A geolocation-based meta-verse NFT project using Web 3.0 API from Moralis and Ethereum smart contract in Solidity (PoC) 	
	- Consulted and designed the software development plan for a Python-web-based voice assistant using a customized voice of the elderly. Designed the blueprint to use	

	the Mozilla TTS (Coqui) with Japanese voice clips transfer learning from Kokoro corpus (WIP)
2016-2020	Ph.D. project: Design and development of Closed Captioning quality assessment method using machine learning to replicate Deaf and Hard of Hearing viewers using Active Learning strategy - Multilayer Perceptron implemented under Keras-Tensorflow
2013-2015	M.Sc. project: Design and development of a vibrotactile composition editor implemented using Java. Presented at the Accessibility Innovation Showcase.
2013	B.Sc. project: Designed and developed a special web browser for elders with Parkinson's (i.e., shaky hands). Used clustering algorithm to find the hovering finger on a tabletop touch input device (Microsoft Surface Tabletop)
2012	Developed a side-scroller game using Nintendo Wii console (<u>teaser</u>) and presented at the Research In Action & Level Up Showcase. Implemented using Unity3D and Blender.

Awards and achievements

Exclusion of research funding

- A Li		
Year	Achievement	
2021	Runner up - oral presentations in Data Analytics, Al & Robotics, UTERC 2021 (\$200)	
2020-2021	University of Toronto MIE Doctoral Completion Award (\$12,000)	
2020	Research grant from the Broadcasting Accessibility Fund, To develop an automated quality assessment system for Closed Captioning, \$92,161	
2016-2020	University of Toronto MIE Graduate Fellowship (\$12,500 annually)	
2018	IEEE AIKE Best Paper	
2016-2021	Graduate Stipendium - issued by Toronto Metropolitan University funding from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council (NSERC) Discovery Canada (\$22,000 annually)	
2015	Governor General Gold Medal nomination for thesis	
2014-2015	Toronto Metropolitan University Graduate Fellowship (\$12,000 annually)	
2013-2015	Graduate Stipendium - issued by Toronto Metropolitan University funding from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council (SSHRC) and GRAND Canada (\$18,000 annually)	
2013-2014	Toronto Metropolitan University Graduate Award (\$8,000)	
2013-2016	Google Code Jam (qualified for three consecutive years, Round 1 for 2013 entry top 20%)	
2006	 Medalist, FIRST (For Inspiration and Recognition of Science and Technology) Vex Robotics official tournament 1st (2006) and 2nd (2005) place in Civil Canada Arm, McMaster Engineering & Science Olympics 	

Peer-reviewed publications & presentations

Life-Time Summary	
Refereed Journal Articles	4
Refereed Conference Proceedings (presentations)	3 (6)
Paper Reviews	4

Selected publications

- Spitschan, M., Mead, J., Roos, C., Lowis, C., Griffiths, B., Mucur, P., Herf, M., Nam, S., & Veitch, J. A. (2022). luox: novel validated open-access and open-source web platform for calculating and sharing physiologically relevant quantities for light and lighting. Wellcome Open Res, 6, 69. doi:10.12688/wellcomeopenres.16595.3 (SJR IF=2.727) (link)
- Nam, S., Fels, D., & Chignell, M. Toward a Subjective Assessment System for Closed Captioning Quality. SMPTE Motion Imaging Journal, 130(3), 35-44, White Plains, NY (2021) (link)
- Nam, S. Designing a Subjective Assessment System for the Quality of Closed Captioning Using Artificial Intelligence. Broadcast Engineering and Information Technology Conference, Washington, USA (2020) (link)
- Nam, S., & Fels, D. Simulation of Subjective Closed Captioning Quality Assessment Using Prediction Models. International Journal of Semantic Computing (ESCI, IF=1.03), 13(01), 45-65.
 (2019) (link)
- Nam, S., & Fels, D. Assessing closed captioning quality using a multilayer perceptron. In 2018
 IEEE First International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Knowledge Engineering (AIKE)
 (pp. 9-16). IEEE. (2018) (link)
- Nam, S., & Fels, D. Design and evaluation of an authoring tool and notation system for vibrotactile composition. International Conference on Universal Access in Human-Computer Interaction (pp. 43-53). Springer, Cham. (2016) (link)

Presentations

- luox An open-source, open-access web platform implementing international standards for the quantification of light, Lightning Talks track, FOSDEM 2022 - Free and Open-source Software Developers' European Meeting, Brussels, Belgium (2022) (link)
- Towards an automatic caption quality assessment model reflecting the subjective views of Deaf, and Hard of Hearing audiences, Oral Presentations in Data Analytics, Al & Robotics, UTERC 2021, Toronto, Canada (2021) (link)
- Towards designing a subjective assessment method for the quality of Closed Captioning using deep neural networks. Internal webinar for OVPECI, Toronto Metropolitan University, Canada (2020)
- Designing a Subjective Assessment System for the Quality of Closed Captioning Using Artificial Intelligence. NAB Show, Las Vegas, USA (2020)

- Nam, S. and Fels, D. Assessing closed captioning quality using a multilayer perceptron. IEEE Artificial Intelligence and Knowledge Engineering, Laguna Hills, California, USA (2018)
- Design and Evaluation of an Authoring Tool and Notation System for Vibrotactile Composition. Human-Computer Interaction International 2016, Toronto, Canada (2016)

Reviews

- IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems (TCSS), 2022
- Graphics Interface (GI 22), 2022
- The Special Interest Group on Computer-Human Interaction (ACM-SIGCHI), 2018
- International Conference on Computers Helping People with Special Needs (ICCHP), 2014

Teaching experience

List of courses that I have participated in as a sessional lecturer or as a (lead) Teaching Assistant (TA). I provided lectures, created course outlines, and designed and held practical tutorials, assignments, projects, and exams.

<u>'</u>		
Adjunct Professor / Lecturer		
2022	CPS613/CP8205 Human-Computer Interaction, Toronto Metropolitan University	
2019 (C)ITM350 Concepts of e-Business, Toronto Metropolitan University		
Lead TA / Substitute Lecturer		
2018	ITM350 Concepts of e-Business, Toronto Metropolitan University	
	MIE344 Ergonomic Design of Information Systems, University of Toronto	
2017 - 2018	MIE253 Data modelling, MS Access, MySQL for OLAP with Java, University of Toronto	
2016 - 2017	ITM780 Web design and Management, JavaScript and HTML5, Toronto Metropolitan University	
2015	ITM445 Multimedia in Business, Adobe Suites, Toronto Metropolitan University	
TA		
2016	CPS209 Computer Science: Object-Oriented Programming, C++, Toronto Metropolitan University	
2015	CPS506 Comparative programming languages, Haskell and Rust, Toronto Metropolitan University	
2014 - 2015	CPS305 Data Structure, Java, Toronto Metropolitan University	
2013 - 2014	CPS125 Digital Computation and Programming, Matlab, Toronto Metropolitan University	
2013	CPS105 Intro to Computer Science, Java, Toronto Metropolitan University	
	CPS118 Introductory Programming for Scientist, C++, Toronto Metropolitan University	

Course development

- CPS613/CP8205, Human-Computer Interaction, created a full course material, assignments, and project. (2022)
- ITM350, Concepts of e-Business, redesigned the course and created projects and assignments. (2018)
- ITM780, Web Design and Management, assisted Professor Deborah Fels in redesigning the course and assignments. (2017)